Guide to the David W. McAleavey papers, 1977-1993 MS2051
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
David W. McAleavey papers
1977-1993
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
McAleavey, David W.
MS2051
4 Linear Feet
Collection consists of administrative files, correspondence, newsletters, manuscripts, videotape cassettes and audiotape cassettes dating from 1976-93 focusing primarily on writers who lived in the Washington, D.C. Metropolitan area during this period. The "Carousel" publications trace the development of the Writer's Center community for almost 18 years.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by David McAleavey to Gelman Library in 1986; McAleavey donated additional copies of the Carousel newsletter in 1993.
Biographical Note
David McAleavey has played an active role in the Washington D.C. literary community, not only as a professor of literature at George Washington University, but also as a poet, a Jenny McKean Moore writing workshop leader, project director, and editor. He served from 1977 to 1980 on the Board of Directors of the Writer's Center, and helped produce the center's newsletter Carousel.
McAleavey taught at Cornell University from 1970-1973, and has been a member of the English Department at the George Washington University since 1974. He gained tenure in 1980, and became a full professor in 1989. He teaches courses in creative writing, American literature, English literature, and composition. McAleavey was Associate Dean for Student Services, Columbian College and Graduate School of Arts and Sciences at GWU from 1986 to 1994.
McAleavey has been a poetry writing instructor in the adult education workshops at the Writer's Center, Glen Echo and Bethesda, Maryland, 1977-1983. In addition, in 1992 he was the facilitator for "Poets in Person" poetry lecture/discussion groups using NEH-supported audiotapes produced by the Modern Poetry Association.
McAleavey's publications include poems in magazines, three books of poetry, and two anthologies that he edited. He has written several scholarly articles and bibliographies on the works of George Oppen and the mid-century American Objectivist poets.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consist of administrative files, correspondence, newsletters, manuscripts, videotape cassettes, and audiotape cassettes. The material is dated from 1976-93. This collection focuses primarily on writers who lived in the Metropolitan area during this period. The "Carousel" publications trace the development of the Writer's Center community for almost 18 years. The materials related to the publication of the Jenny McKean Moore Workshop anthology, "Evidence of Community," record many of the activities of the free community workshops, which were supported by a fund left in trust after the death of the GW student playwright to make college level creative writing courses available to writers in the Washington area who would not otherwise be able to attend them.
The collection includes videotaped recordings of two literary events in which McAleavey was involved. The first is the Larry Neal Writer's Conference, an annual meeting named for Larry Neal (1937-1981), a major figure in the Black Arts Movement of the 1960's. McAleavey served on the steering committee of the conference held on May 10, 1985, which was themed "Writers: A Sense of Place." This conference included some important local and national writers, including prominent Native American writer Louise Erdrich. The second event recorded on videotape was the "Washington and Washington Writing" conference held at George Washington April 18-19, 1986. McAleavey edited an issue of the G.W. Washington Studies series, Washington and Washington Writing, that anthologizes the papers presented by numerous important members of the Washington literary community at this conference. Also in the collection are audiotape recordings of a writing workshop, which include Washington D.C. writers Ann Darr, Jonetta Barras, Gregory Orfalea, and Dan Johnson.
This collection is part of the Washington Writers Archives at Gelman Special Collections, which includes original manuscripts and records from writers's organizations in the Washington D.C. area.
Collection Organization
Organized into five series: Jenny McKean Moore workshops, The Writer's Center, Writer's conferences, Videotape cassettes, and Audiotape cassettes.
Audiocassettes; Videocassettes; Poetry; Conferences; Washington (D.C.); Orfalea, Gregory; Johnson, Dan; Darr, Ann; George Washington University; Barras, Jonetta Rose; Marshall, Gregory
- Jenny McKean Moore Workshops, 1983-1984; MS2051 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is comprises correspondence, and manuscripts and final published versions related to "Evidence of Community: Writing from the Jenny McKean Moore Workshops at George Washington University," the 1984 anthology that McAleavey edited. The material dates from 1983-84.
  - Anthology Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anthology Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anthology Rejections, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anthology Rejections, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anthology Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anthology Notes n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anthology Manuscript [folder 1], undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anthology Manuscript [folder 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anthology Manuscript [folder 3], undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Anthology Manuscript [folder 4], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Anthology Manuscript [folder 5], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Anthology Manuscript [folder 6], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Evidence of Community, edited by David McAleavey, No. 11, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- The Writer's Center, 1977-1993; MS2051 Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series contains issues of the newsletter Carousel, the Writer's Center monthly newsletter. The issues date from 1977-1993. This is not a complete archive of the newsletter; several single issues are missing, and no 1992 issues are represented. David McAleavey served on the Board of Directors of the Writer's Center from 1977-80.
  - Carousel newsletter, n.d., undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Carousel newsletter, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Writer's conferences, 1985-1986; MS2051 Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of program questionnaires, brochures, and registration forms. This material all relates to three Washington D.C. area writer's conferences in which McAleavey took part. Materials related to the May 10, 1985 meeting of the Larry Neal Annual Writer's Conference themed "Writers: A Sense of Place" includes a conference program, various printed brochures, and a questionnaire related to the Washington Writer's Archive Project. Videotaped proceedings of this conference are described in series IV of this collection. Printed materials for the May 18, 1985 meeting of the Washington Independent Writers Spring Writer's Conference include a program and a membership brochure. A brochure stating registration information for the Washington and Washington Writing conference, which met on April 18-19, 1986, is also included in this series. Videotape of this conference is also collected in Series IV.
  - The Larry Neal Annual Writer's Conference Program and Washington Writer's Archive Project questionnaire, 1985 May 10-11 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Larry Neal Annual Writer's Conference brochures, 1985 May 10-11 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Larry Neal Annual Writer's Conference brochures, 1985 May 10-11 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Washington Independent Writers, Spring Writer's Conference program, membership brochure and sticker, 1985 May 18 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Washington and Washington Writing, a Conference, registration information, 1986 April 18-19 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Videotape cassettes, 1985-1986; MS2051 Series 4; 2 Linear feet
  This series is made up of professionally recorded "GWTV" videotape cassettes of two writers conferences held at George Washington University. Contained are six videotapes that record the meeting of the Larry Neal Annual Writer's Conference themed "Writers: A Sense of Place," which was held May 10, 1985. The second series contains 20 tapes from the April 18 and 19, 1986 Washington and Washington Writing Conference. This material dates from 1985-86.
  - Larry Neal Writer's Conference: Remote Production Footage: Opening Remarks, 1985 May 10 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Larry Neal Writer's Conference: Remote Production Footage: Julia Alvarez Speech, 1985 May 10 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Larry Neal Writer's Conference: Remote Production Footage:, 1985 May 10 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Larry Neal Writer's Conference: Remote Production Footage: Keynote Address, 1985 May 10 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Larry Neal Writer's Conference: Remote Production Footage: Keynote Address, 1985 May 10 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Larry Neal Writer's Conference: Louise Erdrich, 1985 May 10 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Cutaway (Tape A), 1986 April 18 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: (Tape B), 1986 April 18 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Alfred Kazin, Keynote Speech, (Tape 1 of 2), 1986 April 18 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Alfred Kazin, Keynote Speech, (Tape 2 of 2), 1986 April 18 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Alan Wade, Lorraine Brown, (Tape 1), 1986 April 19 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Nathan Garner, Donn Murphy, (Tape 2), 1986 April 19 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: E. Ethelbert Miller, Joan Retallack, (Tape 3), 1986 April 19 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Winston Napier, (Tape 4), 1986 April 19 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Al Nielson, Eleanor Traylor, Jeffrey Stewart, (Tape 5), 1986 April 19 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Allan Lefcowitz, Christopher Sten, (Tape 6), 1986 April 19 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Christopher Sten, Jerome Loving, (Tape 7), 1986 April 19 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Jackson Breyer, Henry Taylor, (Tape 8), 1986 April 19 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Closing Address, Reed Whittemore, (Tape 9), 1986 April 19 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Francis Rosenburg, Richard Peabody, "Washington and the Small Press Panel," (Tape 1), 1986 April 19 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Merrill Leffler, Grace Cavalieri, "Washington and the Small Press," panel (Tape 2), 1986 April 19 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Faye Moskowitz, Susan Shreve, Jane Gillette, "Washington Novels and the Novelist" panel, (Tape 3), 1986 April 19 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Jane Gillette, Charles Larson, "Washington Novels and the Novelist" panel, (Tape 4), 1986 April 19 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Gregory Rigley, Arnost Lustig, Alicia Portnoy, Oli Egbuna, "Washington as a scene of International Writing, (Tape 5), 1986 April 19 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: "Washington as a Scene of International Writing" panel, (Tape 6), 1986 April 19 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Washington and Washington Writing Conference: Betty Parry, Josephine Jacobsen, Stanley Kunitz, O.B. Hardison, The Library of Congress Consultancy in Poetry and Washington Writing, (Tape 7), 1986 April 19 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Audiotape cassettes, undated; MS2051 Series 5; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of eight audio recordings of local writers, including Ann Darr, Gregory Marshall, Peter Klappert and Dan Johnson. McAleavey could not recall the event at which these recordings were made. The recording quality of these tapes is not good.
  - Abing, Peter Klappert, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Barbara Berman, Don Colburn, Dorothy Jones, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Ann Darr, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Lynne Dreyer, Susan Sonde, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Lenny Lianne, Lewis Conn, Franklin Montgomery, Craig Reynolds, Paul Hopper, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Cardine Marshall, Dan Johnson, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Gregory Orfalea, Jonetta Barras, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Rika Lesser, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)